YWCA of the U.S.A. Records. Record Group 8. Community Associations
Sophia Smith Collection
- SERIES IV. COMMUNITY ASSOCIATIONS FILES
  The development of a system (adopted at the 1949 Convention) by which Associations were expected to meet a set of "basic standards" in order to remain affiliated with the National Association had a profound effect on the relationship between the YWCA of the USA and its member Associations. As the National Association reduced its program development activities, particularly after World War II, the work of the department charged with providing services to Community Associations became increasingly about monitoring this "basic standards" reporting process and tracking each Association's financial support of the National Association. Once the Action Audit for Change process was adopted in the 1970s, that reporting was also the responsibility of the department.
  While record-keeping related to membership regulations increased, direct service to Community Associations in need of specific help or advice continued, but on a smaller scale and more often by mail or telephone than through a visit from National Staff. As the National Association scaled back its program activities, Community Associations were encouraged to share information about their new programs and methods. The National Office collected such materials for potential adaptation and dissemination to the whole Association. National staff also kept track of local pressures to merge operations with the YMCA and Associations involved in controversies and lawsuits, especially those that had the potential to make a serious negative impact on the National Association. Included in these are lawsuits challenging the all-female board membership policy on sex discrimination grounds (EEOC vs. YWCA of Tucson), and a variety of liability lawsuits and problems with tenants.
  The National Association appears to have begun to keep files on individual Associations with the staff reorganization in 1923. The files created at that time contain some earlier items, particularly information about the original affiliation of Member Associations and copies of constitutions and by-laws. The records of interactions between national staff and individual Associations, including the extensive and rich correspondence and visitation reports, date from 1923 on.
  Included are such topics as relations with branches (usually 'colored' branches, but also International Institutes); progress with racial integration; studies on various topics carried out either by the Association or by a local agency; affiliation/disaffiliation history, lawsuits; and controversies. The files can include Association histories, materials about program, rosters of staff and volunteer leadership, reports on YM-YW cooperation, information about the Association's building, and annual reports. Many also include consultants' reports and special studies on any and all topics of interest to the YWCA, such as race relations, industrial conditions, and youth. These can be a rich source of historical information about individual YWCAs, but they are not particularly comprehensive. What is included is somewhat dependent on what the Community Association thought to send to the National Office.
  After 1930, the Association phased out the extensive written reports of its early years. Though Secretaries continued to file visitation reports, they did not travel as much and the files are much less likely to contain records of extensive interaction with the National Association. Once the Basic Standards system was initiated after World War II, Community Association files tend to primarily contain Basic Standards report forms and updated constitution and affiliation/certification (including dissolution and disaffiliation) history materials. Also included are Action Audit for Change reports on progress toward eliminating institutional racism.
  Community Association files also document inquiries from individuals interested in forming new YWCAs and associated records.
  As with elsewhere in the records, very little survives from 1971-87.
  The later files document the process for "rigorously enforcing adherence to the standards" that was undertaken as a part Project Redesign in 1992. They also contain extensive evidence of deteriorating relations between National and its Community Associations.
  [see Microfilmed Records Reel list]
  Most of the materials in the extensive Local Associations files on the microfilm were discarded after filming. Surviving paper records from that period (1884-1970) are extremely fragmentary. Reel 169, containing the pre-1950 records of some Florida Associations (Gainesville-West Palm Beach) and Georgia Associations (Albany-Brunswick) is lost.
  The microfilmed records include some very early materials, but the bulk are dated after the establishment of the Field Division in 1923.
  The earlier microfilmed Local Associations files are rich sources of information about Associations and their various Branches and International Institutes. Included are YWCA and other organizations' studies and surveys of the local community and particular constituencies within it. These regularly include local interracial, youth, immigration, and industrial studies among other topics. There are also files on YWCA cooperation at the local level with other social service organizations, particularly the YMCA.
  The microfilmed Local Associations files also contain some records of World War I era facilities (filed by location) as well as some records of the Hollywood Studio Club (under California.)
  Filming of the "Local Associations" files was done in three batches: materials covering the years 1884 to 1950; 1951 to 1960; and 1961to 1970. Each batch is arranged alphabetically by state and then alphabetically by location of the Association.
  Please note: The Inventory lists the types of materials that were filmed, but not necessarily in the order in which they appear on the film.
  Original Format Records, 1868-2002, 108 linear feet
  The Paper Records are arranged in two Subseries:
  Subseries A. Community Associations Historical Files
  Most of the materials in the extensive Local Associations files on the microfilm were discarded after filming. Surviving paper records from that period (1884-1970) are extremely fragmentary.
  These files consist primarily of materials assembled by the YWCA Librarian and Archivists to provide historical information about Community Associations. Included are publications, clippings, studies, histories, and reports. There are a few miscellaneous early office records that were transferred from offices after the National Board Archives was established. These may not have been microfilmed. Some major studies and reports on individual Associations that were part of the National Board library collection can be found here. Also included are responses to the National Board Archives Project 1974 questionnaire about historical records held by Associations.
  They are arranged alphabetically by state, then alphabetically by location or name of the Association.
  Subseries B. Community Associations Files
  These files are the equivalent of the Local Associations files on the microfilm, but date between 1988 and 2002. They are the files maintained by the Member Association Services office.
  Included in this series are the various reports and records required for maintaining affiliation with the National Association, such as updated constitution and by-laws, summary financial records, statistical reports and general information on program.
  The correspondence deals with affiliation-related issues, and can also include advisory correspondence, and materials on local controversies, as well as such things as arrangements for visits by national staff. The MAS office also kept track of any lawsuits filed against Community Associations.
  The materials are filed by state and then by the most current name of the Association (as of 2002) with its location/city in parentheses where applicable.
  The earliest records of national staff interactions with Community Associations can be found in the minutes and reports of the departments providing services to associations (Field Work, City, Town, Rural Communities) in SERIES I of this Record Group. These include 1907-23 reports of visits to Associations.
  There is some correspondence with Community Associations in RECORD GROUP 3. NATIONAL ADMINISTRATIVE OFFICE, in SERIES I. GENERAL ADMINISTRATION and in RECORD GROUP 6. PROGRAM, SERIES III. PUBLIC ADVOCACY.
  Materials related to the Action Program for Integration and Desegregation of Community Associations and the Action Audit reporting program can be found in RECORD GROUP 6. PROGRAM, SERIES IV. CONSTITUENT GROUPS, Subseries C. Interracial/Racial Justice.
  The Department of Data and Statistics (in RECORD GROUP 3. NATIONAL ADMINISTRATIVE OFFICE, SERIES 4 ) published compilations of statistics gleaned from report forms submitted by Community Associations.
  Detailed reports from individual Associations affiliated with the two predecessor organizations to the YWCA of the U.S.A. are included in the Conference and Convention Proceedings of those organizations in RECORD GROUP 2. PREDECESSOR ORGANIZATIONS AND NATIONAL BOARD.
  Additional early information about interactions with Associations can be found in the minutes and reports of the State, Territorial, and Field Committees in RECORD GROUP 2. PREDECESSOR ORGANIZATIONS AND NATIONAL BOARD.
  Routine reports on activities of Community Associations can be found in the YWCA of the USA's main serial publication: The Association Monthly/Womans Press/YWCA Magazine/YWCA Interchange in SERIES 6. PUBLICATIONS of RECORD GROUP 6. PROGRAM.
  Similar types of records about Student Associations is in RECORD GROUP 7. STUDENT WORK.
  The Sophia Smith Collection maintains a list of repositories known to hold historical records of Community and Student YWCAs.
- SERIES I. SERVICES TO COMMUNITY ASSOCIATIONS
  This is the Contents List for the Original Format Records only. The reel lists for the Microfilmed Records are in a separate file. See Series Descriptions for historical and scope and content notes.
  - Subseries A. 1907-spring 1932
    - General and History
      - Field Work Department, 1913-20, n.d. (Box 808, Folder 1)
      - Field Committees: By-laws, 1913-21 (Box 808, Folder 2)
      - City Department/Committee
        - General, 1899-1928 (Box 808, Folder 3)
        - Policies and Program, 1909-15 (Box 808, Folder 4)
      - Association Extension Committee, 1914, n.d. (Box 808, Folder 5)
      - Town Department/Committee, 1913-23 (Box 808, Folder 6-7)
      - Rural Communities Department/Committee, 1913-76, n.d. (Box 808, Folder 8)
    - Minutes
      - [Sociological Investigation and] Association Extension Committee, 1907-4 Oct 1912 (Box 808, Folder 9-11)
      - Territorial/Field Work
        - Special Committee on Territorial Work, 1908-Mar 1909 (Box 808, Folder 12)
        - Department of Territorial Work, May 1909-Jan 1910 (Box 808, Folder 13)
        - Department of Field Work
          - Feb 1910-May 1919 (Box 808, Folder 14-21)
          - Jun 1919-May 1921 (Box 809, Folder 1-4)
      - Field Division
        - Committee, Executive Group, staff, and Committee of Management, 1922 (Box 809, Folder 5)
        - Committee, Executive Group, and staff, 1923-Jun 1931 (Box 809, Folder 6-10)
        - Council on Organization, 1924-30 (Box 809, Folder 11-13)
      - City
        - City Committee, 1907-21 (Box 810, Folder 1-11)
        - City Department
          - 1922-25 (Box 810, Folder 12-15)
          - 1928-May 1931 (Box 811, Folder 1-4)
      - Town and Country
        - Small Town and Country Committee, 31 Oct 1912-Apr 1913 (Box 811, Folder 5)
        - Town and Country Committee, Sep 1913-21 (Box 811, Folder 6-10)
        - Town Department
          - 1922-28 (Box 811, Folder 11-16)
          - 1929-May 1931 (Box 812, Folder 1-3)
      - Rural
        - County Department, 1921-22 (Box 812, Folder 4)
        - Rural Communities Department, 1922-Jun 1931 (Box 812, Folder 5-11)
    - Publications
      - "The Study of a Local Field," by Walter M. Wood, 1907 (Box 812, Folder 11a)
      - City
        - General and administration, 1907-22, n.d. (Box 812, Folder 12)
        - Constitutions, 1915, 1929 (Box 812, Folder 13)
        - Membership, 1921, 1927 (Box 812, Folder 14)
        - Residences and Boarding Homes, 1907-30 (Box 812, Folder 15-16)
        - "Community Studies for Young Women's Christian Association Workers in Cities" compiled by the Research Bureau for the City Committee, 1920 (Box 813, Folder 1)
        - "Development of Association Program in Areas Related to Cities: Methods of Work and Suggestions for Preliminary Study," 1928 (Box 813, Folder 2)
        - "Outline for a Study of the Community and Itself by a City Association," City Department reprint, 1928 (Box 813, Folder 3)
        - "The Place of the Young Women's Christian Association in Cities" by Mary S. Sims, TWP 1926;1930 revised edition (Box 813, Folder 4)
      - Town
        - General and Administration, 1914-29, n.d. (Box 813, Folder 5)
        - Constitutions, 1919-29, n.d. (Box 813, Folder 6)
        - "A Community Study for Town Associations," n.d. (Box 813, Folder 7)
        - "Suggestions for Education Committees of YWCAs in Towns," n.d. (Box 813, Folder 8)
      - Rural
        - General, 1908-26 (Box 813, Folder 9)
        - "How Can We Interest Our Community in the YWCA," draft for a leaflet, 22 Apr 1930 (Box 813, Folder 10)
    - Reports
      - Field Work
        - State Adjustment Committee, 1907 (Box 813, Folder 11)
        - Special Committee on Territorial Work, 1908 (Box 813, Folder 12)
        - Chair, Executive Secretary, and Office Secretary, 1909-18 (Box 813, Folder 13-17)
        - Secretary reports
          - Miscellaneous, 1911-20 (Box 814, Folder 1)
          - Marion E. Hopkins, Cafeterias, 1920-21 (Box 814, Folder 2-3)
          - Northwestern Territorial Committee: annual reports, 1910-11 (Box 814, Folder 4)
      - Field Division
        - Miscellaneous, 1919-27 (Box 814, Folder 5)
        - Employment and Room Registry (Emma Phinney), 1924-29 (Box 814, Folder 6-7)
        - Food Service
          - Marion Hopkins, 1922-30 (Box 814, Folder 8-13)
          - Margaret Proctor, 1923-24 (Box 814, Folder 14)
        - Case Study of a Village in Mississippi by Marjorie Patten, 1931 (Box 814, Folder 15)
        - Report of the Survey of Western Massachusetts, 1929 (Box 814, Folder 16)
      - City
        - Chair and Vice-Chair reports to National Board, 1907-25 (Box 814, Folder 17-18)
        - Secretary annual and periodic reports
          - Edith S. Aykroyd, 1920-21 (Box 814, Folder 19)
          - Margaret Alton, 1920 (Box 814, Folder 20)
          - Helen D. Beavers, 1921-23 (Box 814, Folder 21)
          - Elizabeth Boies, 1909-17 (Box 814, Folder 22)
          - Eva D. Bowles, 1913-30 (Box 814, Folder 23-26)
          - Edith (Terry) Bremer, 1911-16 (Box 815, Folder 1)
          - Anna L. Brown, 1909-16 (Box 815, Folder 2-3)
          - Amy Gordon Bruce, 1922 (Box 815, Folder 4)
          - Elsie I. Burnham, 1931 (Box 815, Folder 5)
          - Margaret L. Burton, 1913-14, 1927 (Box 815, Folder 6)
          - Mary S. Bushnell, 1910-12 (Box 815, Folder 7)
          - Eliza R. Butler, 1913 (Box 815, Folder 8)
          - Mary L. Cady, 1918-20 (Box 815, Folder 9)
          - Julia F. Capen, 1920-29 (Box 815, Folder 10-14)
          - Harriet R. Chamberlin, 1922 (Box 815, Folder 15)
          - Frances M. Crittenden, 1922 (Box 815, Folder 16)
          - Mary Frances Day, 1924-31 (Box 815, Folder 17-20)
          - Mary E. Dunbar, 1922 (Box 815, Folder 21)
          - Marcia O. Dunham, 1911-14 (Box 815, Folder 22)
          - Mary S. Dunn, 1907-09 (Box 815, Folder 23)
          - Jeanette Dutchess, 1921-31 (Box 815, Folder 24-29)
          - Lena M. Farrar, 1919-30 (Box 816, Folder 1-4)
          - Mary C. Ferris, 1928-31 (Box 816, Folder 5)
          - Marie Foulkes, 1919 (Box 816, Folder 6)
          - Erie Layton Gates, 1922-25 (Box 816, Folder 7-8)
          - Blanche Geary, 1910-20 (Box 816, Folder 9-10)
          - Margaret B. Gerard, 1929-30 (Box 816, Folder 11)
          - Annie Kate Gilbert, 1920-28 (Box 816, Folder 12-13)
          - Gertrude Gogin, 1917-20 (Box 816, Folder 14)
          - Gertrude Griffith, 1911-16 (Box 816, Folder 15)
          - Maud L. Harrison, 1920 (Box 816, Folder 16)
          - Elizabeth (Ross) Haynes, 1909-12 (Box 816, Folder 17)
          - Emma Hays, 1909 (Box 816, Folder 18)
          - Cecelia Holloway, 1911 (Box 816, Folder 19)
          - Louise S. Holmquist, 1909-13 (Box 816, Folder 20)
          - Addie W. Hunton, 1911-14 (Box 816, Folder 21)
          - Imogene B. Ireland, 1920 (Box 816, Folder 22)
          - Mary E. Jackson, 1918-20 (Box 816, Folder 23)
          - Jean E. James, 1919 (Box 816, Folder 24)
          - Eleanor Larrabee Lattimore, 1920 (Box 816, Folder 25)
          - Genevieve Lowry, 1931 (Box 816, Folder 26)
          - Josephine F. Lynch, 1919 (Box 816, Folder 27)
          - Leona Macgeorge, 1922 (Box 816, Folder 28)
          - Hazel MacKaye, 1919-20 (Box 816, Folder 29)
          - Louise MacMaster, 1919-22 (Box 816, Folder 30)
          - Essie L. Maguire, 1931 (Box 817, Folder 1)
          - Mary E. Musson, 1918 (Box 817, Folder 2)
          - Marion H. Nicolovius, 1920-23 (Box 817, Folder 3)
          - Grace L. Osborn, 1922-27 (Box 817, Folder 4)
          - Marion Peabody, 1926-29 (Box 817, Folder 5-6)
          - Matilda Peper, 1909 (Box 817, Folder 7)
          - Lena M. Phillips, 1919 (Box 817, Folder 8)
          - Emma Phinney, 1920-29 (Box 817, Folder 9-12)
          - Mary Preston, 1927-29 (Box 817, Folder 13)
          - Margaret Swain Pratt, 1920 (Box 817, Folder 14)
          - Margaret A. Proctor, 1918-20 (Box 817, Folder 15)
          - Lucile Rader, 1929 (Box 817, Folder 16)
          - Susan M. Rebhan, 1922-23 (Box 817, Folder 17)
          - Alice R. Reynolds, 1922-31 (Box 817, Folder 18-23)
          - Anna V. Rice, 1913-20 (Box 817, Folder 24-25)
          - Elizabeth A. Ross, [see Elizabeth (Ross) Haynes]
          - Adela F. Ruffin, 1922-24 (Box 818, Folder 1)
          - Mary E. Rust, 1920 (Box 818, Folder 2)
          - Helen Rysdorp, 1928-31 (Box 818, Folder 3)
          - Helen B. Schuyler, 1927-31 (Box 818, Folder 4-6)
          - Mary E. Scott, 1923-31 (Box 818, Folder 7-10)
          - Grace Sheppard, 1920 (Box 818, Folder 11)
          - Florence Simms, 1912-20 (Box 818, Folder 12-13)
          - Mary Sims, 1914-30 (Box 818, Folder 14-17)
          - Marie Lutters Stanton, 1920 (Box 818, Folder 18)
          - E. Beatrice Stearns, 1920 (Box 818, Folder 19)
          - Marguerite K. Sylla
            - 1922-27 (Box 818, Folder 20-22)
            - 1928-31 (Box 819, Folder 1-2)
          - Edith Baldwin Terry, [see Edith (Terry) Bremer]
          - Helen L. Thomas, 1909-16 (Box 819, Folder 3-4)
          - Harriet S. Vance, 1922-23 (Box 819, Folder 5)
          - Laura Vossler, 1918-19 (Box 819, Folder 6)
          - Harriet Wilde, 1919-20 (Box 819, Folder 7)
          - Margaret Williamson, 1917-25 (Box 819, Folder 8-10)
          - Sue Ann Wilson, 1920 (Box 819, Folder 11)
          - Cordella A. Winn, 1922-31 (Box 819, Folder 12-16)
          - Helen W. Wise, 1923-31 (Box 819, Folder 17-21)
          - Bertha J. Woodward, 1919 (Box 820, Folder 1)
          - Laura H. Young, 1922-24 (Box 820, Folder 2)
      - Town
        - Association Extension Committee
          - Chair report to National Board, 1907-19 (Box 820, Folder 3-5)
          - Biennial report, 1909-10 (Box 820, Folder 6)
        - Town Department
          - Biennial Report, 1920-21, 1926-27, 1928-29 (Box 820, Folder 7-9)
          - Report of the Department, 3 Mar 1924 (Box 820, Folder 10)
        - Miscellaneous
          - Findings on Occupation of the Field, Town Department and Staff Meeting, 21-23 Apr 1928 (Box 820, Folder 11)
          - Recommendations made and adopted at the sectional meeting of delegates from town Associations, April 26, 1922, during the national convention (Box 820, Folder 12)
          - Reports of the Commissions to study various aspects of the Town program, given at Town Meeting at Convention, 1926 (Box 820, Folder 13)
        - Secretary annual, biennial, and periodic
          - Miscellaneous, 1920-30 (Box 820, Folder 14)
          - Fannie O. Ames, 1918-19 (Box 820, Folder 15)
          - Vera Barger, 1919 (Box 820, Folder 16)
          - Helen F. Barnes, 1909-11 (Box 820, Folder 17)
          - Lavinia Bonner, 1922-24 (Box 820, Folder 18)
          - Frances Bothwell, 1921-24 (Box 820, Folder 19)
          - Eva D. Bowles, 1913 (Box 820, Folder 20)
          - Edith Terry Bremer, 1912 (Box 820, Folder 21)
          - Rachel Brooks, 1917-20 (Box 820, Folder 22)
          - Anna L. Brown, 1909-18 (Box 820, Folder 23)
          - Helen Orr Brown, 1926 (Box 820, Folder 24)
          - Elise I. Burnham, 1924-31 (Box 820, Folder 25-26)
          - Mary L. Cady, 1919-20 (Box 820, Folder 27)
          - Anna M. Clark, 1919-21 (Box 820, Folder 28)
          - Ethel H. Clark, 1919-20 (Box 820, Folder 29)
          - Gretchen L. Coon, 1922 (Box 820, Folder 30)
          - Mildred Corbett
            - 1921-23 (Box 820, Folder 31)
            - 1924-29 (Box 821, Folder 1-3)
          - Lillie V. Cromwell and Jane Dickey, 1929 (Box 821, Folder 4)
          - Ethel Cutler, 1915-17 (Box 821, Folder 5)
          - Sarah B. Deitrick, 1922 (Box 821, Folder 6)
          - Jane Dickey, 1926-29 (Box 821, Folder 7)
          - Jane Dickey and Mary Jane Fisher, 1927-28 (Box 821, Folder 8)
          - Lois Diehl, 1922-25 (Box 821, Folder 9-10)
          - Mildred H. Esgar, 1923-28, 1930 (Box 821, Folder 11-14)
          - Mrs. Charles T. Evans, 1924-25 (Box 821, Folder 15)
          - Lena M. Farrar, 1919 (Box 821, Folder 16)
          - Jessie Field, 1912-17 (Box 821, Folder 17-18)
          - Mary Jane Fisher, 1928-30 (Box 821, Folder 19)
          - Blanche Geary, 1920 (Box 821, Folder 20)
          - Gertrude Ann Geopfarth, 1923-24 (Box 821, Folder 21)
          - Abbie Graham, 1915 (Box 821, Folder 22)
          - Gertrude Gogin, 1918-20 (Box 822, Folder 1)
          - Mabel Head, 1919 (Box 822, Folder 2)
          - Louise Holmquist, 1909-17 (Box 822, Folder 3)
          - M. Esther Huckins, 1925-31 (Box 822, Folder 4-8)
          - M. Esther Huckins and Jane Dickey, 1926-27 (Box 822, Folder 9)
          - Addie W. Hunton, 1912-13 (Box 822, Folder 10)
          - Belle Ingels, 1927-31 (Box 822, Folder 11-14)
          - Elizabeth Jenkins, 1920 (Box 822, Folder 15)
          - Lucile Lippitt, 1926-31 (Box 822, Folder 16-18)
          - Kate Logan, 1917-19 (Box 822, Folder 19)
          - Lillian Long, 1907-11 (Box 822, Folder 20)
          - Ethel Landfear, 1915-16 (Box 822, Folder 21)
          - Eleanor Larrabee Lattimore, 1920 (Box 822, Folder 22)
          - Hazel MacKaye, 1919-20 (Box 822, Folder 23)
          - Essie L. Maguire, 1928-31 (Box 822, Folder 24-25)
          - Bertha I. Miller, 1921-27 (Box 822, Folder 1-4)
          - Jean C. Moore, 1921-22 (Box 822, Folder 5)
          - Margaret Proctor, 1918-19 (Box 822, Folder 6)
          - Clarinda Richards, 1918-19 (Box 822, Folder 7)
          - Lucy B. Richmond, 1919 (Box 822, Folder 8)
          - Clara S. Roe, 1922-30 (Box 822, Folder 9-13)
          - Ebertha Roelofs, 1922-24 (Box 822, Folder 14-15)
          - Helen B. Schuyler, 1921-27 (Box 822, Folder 16-19)
          - Anna Seaburg, 1909-15, 1918-20, 1922-27 (Box 824, Folder 1-3)
          - Ruth Shallcross, 1931 (Box 824, Folder 4)
          - Florence Simms, 1909-12, 1919 (Box 824, Folder 5)
          - Gretta Smith, 1928-31 (Box 824, Folder 6-7)